<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" href="styles.css"?>
<rss
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:media="http://www.rssboard.org/media-rss" version="2.0">
	<channel>		
		<item>
			<title>&#128515;</title>
			<category>rss</category>
			<dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 04:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
			<link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2019/7/23/title</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5d3690287b0795000199f22a</guid>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[<html><p>Body</p></html>]]>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>My Personal Organization System</title>
			<category>designops</category>
			<dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 21:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
			<link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2019/5/2/my-personal-organization-system</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5ccb8561f4e1fcdaca4dc4c8</guid>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[<p class="">I’ve always thought a lot about organization but have never written it down documented exactly how I do certain things. It’s always been more of an abstract idea than anything else. I’m largely autonomous and while the adjustment hasn’t been easy coming from an IC role, I felt I needed more structure to my day but it was then up to me to figure out exactly how to do that. So here it is, all documented and prepped, just for you.</p><p class="">The way I organize my work life has an affect on everyone else I’m working with. My role provides me with responsibility inside and outside my team. That responsibility isn’t lost on me. That’s why I developed this concrete organization system that works for my day-to-day — it’s a <em>framework for getting things done</em>, based on what I know about myself. But it serves a few other purposes:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class=""><strong>Buy-in:</strong> It’s something my manager could easily point to to validate the work we do for buy-in. </p></li><li><p class=""><strong>Accountability:</strong> It’s also an accountability system. By creating this and sharing it, it’s something I have to continue to do and work on.</p></li><li><p class=""><strong>Trust:</strong> Becoming someone your team can depend on builds their trust in you. <a href="https://thedigitalprojectmanager.com/pm-personal-organization-system/" target="_blank">Here’s more about that</a>.</p></li><li><p class=""><strong>Force multiplier:</strong> This is something Julie Zhou talks about a lot. I have to be able to create things that make my team and other teams more efficient. </p></li></ul><p class="">With all that said, here goes. </p><p class="">A set of methods and tools I used to stay organized and push projects forward. Generally speaking, everything (tasks, notes, random ideas, etc.) should have a place and a purpose to keep my day structured and manageable.</p><p class="">First off, there’s a couple overarching methodologies I subscribe to:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">The first is what I call <strong>Proactive Time Chunking or PTC</strong>, because I really love the efficiency of a good acronym. What this is, is an hour that I take every single morning to work on the most important tasks of my day. The day before, I spend an hour at the end of the day prioritizing everything I have to work on and then determining what is going to be the most important thing for the next day or the thing that I'm going to focus on in the morning.<br>The main reason I do this, is because I know I’m the most effective in the morning. I've identified that about myself. I know I'm going to do my best work and I know that 9 times out of 10 I'm not going to have any distractions that early in the morning because most people don’t get there till around ten.</p></li><li><p class=""><a href="https://zenhabits.net/zen-to-done-ztd-the-ultimate-simple-productivity-system/" target="_blank">Zen-to-done</a>: this is comprised of two main pieces: the first is focusing on one task at a time and being vigilant about it. It's really easy to multitask and I know that I’m not good at multitasking. The second piece of this is timing my tasks or carving out time in my day to work on very specific things. Breaking down each task helps.</p></li></ol><p class=""><strong>Google suite</strong> (docs, sheets, slides, cal, mail) are the obvious go-to. I couldn’t get anything done without them. Nothing out of the ordinary here, but feel like it’s worth mentioning.&nbsp;Here’s the key points:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">Gmail = the new scheduler is key, it let’s me send emails without the stress of sending emails. So if I know I’ll need a little more time to sit with an idea or let something rattle around in my head I’ll just schedule the send for later in the day or even the next day after I’ve gotten the chance to sleep on it.</p></li><li><p class="">Google Calendar = nothing exists unless it’s on my calendar. In addition to meetings and events, this is where I keep “sticky” reminders, aka, things that I can’t afford to forget. I also keep reminders here that affect other teams.&nbsp;</p></li><li><p class="">Slides = presenting ideas in a way that’s easy to understand is a huge part of my job. Being able to condense complex information down to the nuts and bolts and make it visual is a skill that I needed to develop. </p></li></ul><p class=""><strong>Confluence</strong> - this is my “bread and butter”. Documentation is so important in any organization, especially in tech. This kind of highly-specialized, specific knowledge needs to be transferrable inside of companies for a couple major reasons:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">People leave the company</p></li><li><p class="">It becomes super inefficient to constantly ask the same questions (and answer the same questions) over an over again&nbsp;</p></li></ul><p class="">Keeping a knowledge base updated is hard but necessary. I’m still figuring this one out, but it centers around the trio of documentation, education and process somehow. They’re all intertwined and need to be treated as such.</p><p class=""><strong>Timer extension</strong> = I mentioned the Zen to Done methodology. This is the second piece of that. Any old timer will do. It’s to make sure I’m working on the right task for the right amount of time during the day. My day will often be stacked with meetings so knowing what I can work on between those meetings is important for me. As they say, it matters not what the tool is, but how you use it.&nbsp;</p><p class=""><strong>TextEdit</strong> = Everything starts as a text doc. It’s as bare-bones as it gets. I jot down quick notes during meetings, any straggling thoughts during the day and even blog post snippets as they come to me. From there, they get turned into whatever the final thing is. I prune those notes at the end of every week to make sure everything gets turned into something else. A text doc is really just a temporary format. How temporary depends on the note. </p><p class=""><strong>Wrike</strong> = this is where it gets interesting. Every company has a project management system, ours just happens to be Wrike. I use it for everything, you might call me a power user. I keep a lot of project-based info in here for visibility for my manager. The notes that are jotted down in TextEdit may get transferred into Wrike when the time comes and I’ve been able to synthesize that information and condense it in a way that makes sense. So a more polished version of the brain dump that happens during meetings, goes into Wrike.&nbsp;We also use it for task management and form requests for our team.</p><p class=""><strong>Slack</strong> = yep, we use it too. Primarily for communication, but I use it for a couple other interesting things. It’s where I keep reminders for recurring, but low-impact reminders. For example, I might use it to remind me to follow up with someone about a message I need to act on the next day. We also may use it to flag anything that needs to be documented.&nbsp;I swear, documentation is so important.</p><p class=""><strong>Sketch</strong>. = everyone needs to learn Sketch or some design program to finesse those slide decks. We’re lucky, we have a pretty robust slides template to work off of, but having the design background and ability to create something cool on the fly that gets your point across is part of what makes me good.&nbsp;</p><p class="">That’s it. That’s how I keep myself organized. </p>]]>
			</description>
			<media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5ccb8561f4e1fcdaca4dc4c8/1560289638462/1500w/marketers_hugo_sm-1560x760.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="781" height="760">
				<media:title type="plain">My Personal Organization System</media:title>
			</media:content>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
