<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Generated by Site-Server v6.0.0-19018-19018 (http://www.squarespace.com) on Tue, 23 Jul 2019 04:44:10 GMT
--><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://www.rssboard.org/media-rss" version="2.0"><channel><title>Writing - James | Digital Producer, Digital Producer, Design in Brooklyn, NY</title><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/</link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 04:42:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><language>en-US</language><generator>Site-Server v6.0.0-19018-19018 (http://www.squarespace.com)</generator><description></description><item><title>Title</title><category>rss</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 04:42:30 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2019/7/23/title</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5d3690287b0795000199f22a</guid><description><![CDATA[<p class="">Body</p>]]></description></item><item><title>My Personal Organization System</title><category>designops</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 21:46:54 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2019/5/2/my-personal-organization-system</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5ccb8561f4e1fcdaca4dc4c8</guid><description><![CDATA[<p class="">I’ve always thought a lot about organization but have never written it down documented exactly how I do certain things. It’s always been more of an abstract idea than anything else. I’m largely autonomous and while the adjustment hasn’t been easy coming from an IC role, I felt I needed more structure to my day but it was then up to me to figure out exactly how to do that. So here it is, all documented and prepped, just for you.</p><p class="">The way I organize my work life has an affect on everyone else I’m working with. My role provides me with responsibility inside and outside my team. That responsibility isn’t lost on me. That’s why I developed this concrete organization system that works for my day-to-day — it’s a <em>framework for getting things done</em>, based on what I know about myself. But it serves a few other purposes:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class=""><strong>Buy-in:</strong> It’s something my manager could easily point to to validate the work we do for buy-in. </p></li><li><p class=""><strong>Accountability:</strong> It’s also an accountability system. By creating this and sharing it, it’s something I have to continue to do and work on.</p></li><li><p class=""><strong>Trust:</strong> Becoming someone your team can depend on builds their trust in you. <a href="https://thedigitalprojectmanager.com/pm-personal-organization-system/" target="_blank">Here’s more about that</a>.</p></li><li><p class=""><strong>Force multiplier:</strong> This is something Julie Zhou talks about a lot. I have to be able to create things that make my team and other teams more efficient. </p></li></ul><p class="">With all that said, here goes. </p><p class="">A set of methods and tools I used to stay organized and push projects forward. Generally speaking, everything (tasks, notes, random ideas, etc.) should have a place and a purpose to keep my day structured and manageable.</p><p class="">First off, there’s a couple overarching methodologies I subscribe to:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">The first is what I call <strong>Proactive Time Chunking or PTC</strong>, because I really love the efficiency of a good acronym. What this is, is an hour that I take every single morning to work on the most important tasks of my day. The day before, I spend an hour at the end of the day prioritizing everything I have to work on and then determining what is going to be the most important thing for the next day or the thing that I'm going to focus on in the morning.<br>The main reason I do this, is because I know I’m the most effective in the morning. I've identified that about myself. I know I'm going to do my best work and I know that 9 times out of 10 I'm not going to have any distractions that early in the morning because most people don’t get there till around ten.</p></li><li><p class=""><a href="https://zenhabits.net/zen-to-done-ztd-the-ultimate-simple-productivity-system/" target="_blank">Zen-to-done</a>: this is comprised of two main pieces: the first is focusing on one task at a time and being vigilant about it. It's really easy to multitask and I know that I’m not good at multitasking. The second piece of this is timing my tasks or carving out time in my day to work on very specific things. Breaking down each task helps.</p></li></ol><p class=""><strong>Google suite</strong> (docs, sheets, slides, cal, mail) are the obvious go-to. I couldn’t get anything done without them. Nothing out of the ordinary here, but feel like it’s worth mentioning.&nbsp;Here’s the key points:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">Gmail = the new scheduler is key, it let’s me send emails without the stress of sending emails. So if I know I’ll need a little more time to sit with an idea or let something rattle around in my head I’ll just schedule the send for later in the day or even the next day after I’ve gotten the chance to sleep on it.</p></li><li><p class="">Google Calendar = nothing exists unless it’s on my calendar. In addition to meetings and events, this is where I keep “sticky” reminders, aka, things that I can’t afford to forget. I also keep reminders here that affect other teams.&nbsp;</p></li><li><p class="">Slides = presenting ideas in a way that’s easy to understand is a huge part of my job. Being able to condense complex information down to the nuts and bolts and make it visual is a skill that I needed to develop. </p></li></ul><p class=""><strong>Confluence</strong> - this is my “bread and butter”. Documentation is so important in any organization, especially in tech. This kind of highly-specialized, specific knowledge needs to be transferrable inside of companies for a couple major reasons:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">People leave the company</p></li><li><p class="">It becomes super inefficient to constantly ask the same questions (and answer the same questions) over an over again&nbsp;</p></li></ul><p class="">Keeping a knowledge base updated is hard but necessary. I’m still figuring this one out, but it centers around the trio of documentation, education and process somehow. They’re all intertwined and need to be treated as such.</p><p class=""><strong>Timer extension</strong> = I mentioned the Zen to Done methodology. This is the second piece of that. Any old timer will do. It’s to make sure I’m working on the right task for the right amount of time during the day. My day will often be stacked with meetings so knowing what I can work on between those meetings is important for me. As they say, it matters not what the tool is, but how you use it.&nbsp;</p><p class=""><strong>TextEdit</strong> = Everything starts as a text doc. It’s as bare-bones as it gets. I jot down quick notes during meetings, any straggling thoughts during the day and even blog post snippets as they come to me. From there, they get turned into whatever the final thing is. I prune those notes at the end of every week to make sure everything gets turned into something else. A text doc is really just a temporary format. How temporary depends on the note. </p><p class=""><strong>Wrike</strong> = this is where it gets interesting. Every company has a project management system, ours just happens to be Wrike. I use it for everything, you might call me a power user. I keep a lot of project-based info in here for visibility for my manager. The notes that are jotted down in TextEdit may get transferred into Wrike when the time comes and I’ve been able to synthesize that information and condense it in a way that makes sense. So a more polished version of the brain dump that happens during meetings, goes into Wrike.&nbsp;We also use it for task management and form requests for our team.</p><p class=""><strong>Slack</strong> = yep, we use it too. Primarily for communication, but I use it for a couple other interesting things. It’s where I keep reminders for recurring, but low-impact reminders. For example, I might use it to remind me to follow up with someone about a message I need to act on the next day. We also may use it to flag anything that needs to be documented.&nbsp;I swear, documentation is so important.</p><p class=""><strong>Sketch</strong>. = everyone needs to learn Sketch or some design program to finesse those slide decks. We’re lucky, we have a pretty robust slides template to work off of, but having the design background and ability to create something cool on the fly that gets your point across is part of what makes me good.&nbsp;</p><p class="">That’s it. That’s how I keep myself organized. </p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5ccb8561f4e1fcdaca4dc4c8/1560289638462/1500w/marketers_hugo_sm-1560x760.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="781" height="760"><media:title type="plain">My Personal Organization System</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Spreadsheets to Sketch and everything in between</title><category>designops</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 21:42:04 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2019/4/19/spreadsheets-to-sketch-and-everything-in-between</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5cb9a2bce2c483cdc0ec05d7</guid><description><![CDATA[&nbsp;<blockquote><p class="">Hey, what do you do?</p></blockquote><p class=""><em>tl;dr:<br>I’ve taken on a role that’s a culmination of my 6-year career in tech. I’m on our DesignOps team. More specifically, I’m a Digital Producer for our client-side design team. It’s basically a Digital Project Management position that allows me to use the full range of my experience to push different initiatives forward.&nbsp;</em></p><hr /><p class="">It’s a hard question for some. Harder than most, for those in tech.&nbsp;</p><p class="">So…what do I do? For the longest time, I had no idea. Between what I was doing and what I wanted to do, it was a difficult question to answer. My mom would ask and could never give her a straight answer. Friends with whom I’d lost touch ask and never came away with an answer they could recite back to me. Throughout my 6-year career I’ve wafted from one technical discipline to another. I’ve been a technical writer at a legal firm, copywriter for an ad agency, engineer for a marketing agency and freelance designer, working (not always successfully) for myself.&nbsp;</p><p class="">That’s why the answer to this question has eluded me.&nbsp;</p><p class="">Well that’s changed a bit. I’ve brought together all of that knowledge and experience into something I can say —&nbsp; pretty succinctly. I’m in DesignOps. For those in tech, yes it’s that buzzy word that people have been talking about for a little while. Adding <em>-ops</em> to existing disciplines is a cool thing to do. You can slap <em>-ops</em> on the back of any word really and it automatically elevates that thing. It’s especially cool if it’s a discipline that’s fuzzier, or harder to measure, because it gives your job title a little more heft. </p><p class="">I’ve always wanted to facilitate the work that creatives do. I’m a creative myself but in a different way. From an early age I’ve been a chameleon. Being able to seamlessly blend into different environments allowed me the opportunity to gain these really unique insights from all over and leverage them to offer up a brand new perspective.&nbsp;</p><p class="">Because of that, I consider myself as<strong> </strong>more of<strong> a vector who brings different disciplines and groups of people together to make stuff happen</strong>. Whether that’s building a spreadsheet to get some data or designing assets for a deck, my creativity comes through the solutions I come up with.</p><p class="">So that’s what I do now. I’m immersing myself in the culture, in the industry and hope to come away with some experiences that prove valuable to myself, the team and the company.</p>&nbsp;]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5cb9a2bce2c483cdc0ec05d7/1556550951193/1500w/undraw_organizing_projects1_47ja.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="998"><media:title type="plain">Spreadsheets to Sketch and everything in between</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Writing is good for me</title><category>personal-essay</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 20:08:33 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2018/9/10/writing-is-good-for-me</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5b96cf228a922de250fd7caa</guid><description><![CDATA[&nbsp;<p>10 years ago, I quit playing basketball, which my identity up until then, had been wrapped up in. I’d broken up with a girl I was convinced I was in love with.<br>I was depressed, though I didn’t know it at the time. I was living in Florida, an unfamiliar setting to my story, devoid of anyone to talk to.<br>I opened the notebook I was using for class, to the back where the empty pages were. In red ink, scratched words in a spiral shape, starting from the outside, until I reached the center and couldn’t write anymore. I did the same on the next page.</p><p>And the next and the next.</p><p>Until I didn’t have anything else to say. Until the words negated the sadness.<br>That next semester, back in North Carolina, I signed up for the school newspaper covering arts and culture on campus.<br>I knew one thing for sure after that. I liked writing.</p>&nbsp;]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5b96cf228a922de250fd7caa/1545517034041/1500w/C04B0325.JPG" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Writing is good for me</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>An Artistic Journey</title><category>ws-monthly</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 18:01:26 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/11/22/an-artistic-journey</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5a15bb5d085229dccc0b8a18</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>A story with Winston-Salem Monthly Magazine, as part of their <em>Creative Collective</em> series.</p><p><a href="http://www.journalnow.com/winstonsalemmonthly/creative-collective/an-artistic-journey/article_21b1787c-5a7c-5c64-8205-66f9a280f5f0.html" target="_blank">Link to article</a></p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5a15bb5d085229dccc0b8a18/1545269216201/1500w/1ibis.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="700" height="544"><media:title type="plain">An Artistic Journey</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Sights and Sounds</title><category>ws-monthly</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 17:52:41 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/11/22/sights-and-sounds</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5a15b652e4966b134259bde2</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>An article with Winston-Salem Monthly Magazine, as part of their <em>Creative Collective</em> series.</p><p><a href="http://www.journalnow.com/winstonsalemmonthly/twin-city-talk/sights-and-sounds/article_e3c499ec-4dab-516d-85a2-6149acd81c5a.html" target="_blank">Link to article</a></p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5a15b652e4966b134259bde2/1545269227247/1500w/516ef2f6d7e95.image.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="400" height="266"><media:title type="plain">Sights and Sounds</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Bold Beauty</title><category>ws-monthly</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/11/22/bold-beauty</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5a15bb010d92971bbc4bbf31</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>A story with Winston-Salem Monthly Magazine, as part of their <em>Creative Collective</em> series.</p><p><a href="http://www.journalnow.com/winstonsalemmonthly/creative-collective/bold-beauty/article_f3c96e2e-b159-5ac2-ade1-285a122fc439.html" target="_blank">Link to article</a></p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5a15bb010d92971bbc4bbf31/1545269235660/1500w/516ef327c1334.image.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="600" height="399"><media:title type="plain">Bold Beauty</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Writing as Therapy</title><category>ws-monthly</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 17:58:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/11/22/writing-as-therapy</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5a15ba9941920213696ebd3e</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>A story with Winston-Salem Monthly Magazine, as part of their <em>Creative Collective </em>series.</p><p><a href="http://www.journalnow.com/winstonsalemmonthly/creative-collective/writing-as-therapy/article_c51ed7c9-4703-536d-b939-7b60463b36c5.html" target="_blank">Link to article</a></p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5a15ba9941920213696ebd3e/1545269390770/1500w/516ef70e58d36.image.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="600" height="779"><media:title type="plain">Writing as Therapy</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Higher Goals for Higher Education</title><category>ws-monthly</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 16:54:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/11/22/higher-goals-for-higher-education</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5a15b9b2f9619afa6aa5a454</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>A featured story with Winston-Salem Monthly Magazine.</p><p><a href="http://www.journalnow.com/winstonsalemmonthly/features/higher-goals-for-higher-education/article_6ed447b7-3780-5ac3-9ac4-57d96e79895a.html" target="_blank">Link to article</a></p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5a15b9b2f9619afa6aa5a454/1545269399521/1500w/516ef769d67b1.image.jpg" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="400" height="600"><media:title type="plain">Higher Goals for Higher Education</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>How We Use Asana</title><category>project-management</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:57:45 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/5/17/how-we-use-asana</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:591cf0b6f7e0ab48fd7625e7</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Asana’s hierarchical structure mirrors how we think about our agency and its’ work, so it makes a lot of sense for our team and others like it.<br>From the <strong>Organization</strong> umbrella, to Teams and on down to Projects and Tasks, I’ll outline how we use each one and a couple other of Asana’s features we use and how they integrate into our workflow.</p><p>Asana’s hierarchical structure mirrors how we think about our agency and its’ work, so it makes a lot of sense for our team and others like it. From the Organization umbrella, to Teams and on down to Projects and Tasks, I’ll outline how we use each one and a couple other of Asana’s features we use and how they integrate into our workflow. &nbsp;</p><h2>Organization</h2><p><strong>Organization</strong>&nbsp;is all-encompassing,&nbsp;everything else falls under it. You can have multiple Organizations within the same account, like if you wanted one for work and one for personal use, for example. We each belong to an Organization we've named “activatorstudios”, that holds our Teams, Projects and Tasks. &nbsp;</p><h2>Teams</h2><p>The way our company is structured, at times we all have our hands in everything so we thought the best way to make use of the <strong>Teams</strong>&nbsp;was to separate them in two 1)&nbsp;<strong>Internal Projects </strong>and 2)&nbsp;<strong>Client Projects</strong>. We’re all members of both. All the work we have to get done can then fall under those two categories. The nature of our company, our clients and the work we do for them, means we all need to be a part of every major project. What this also does is provide a high level transparency you don’t often find at agencies like ours. &nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Conversations/Calendar </strong>Inside each Team, there are a couple things going on. The first being <strong>Conversations</strong>. While probably useful, it’s taken a backseat to Slack. The threaded conversations are nice (a feature that <a href="https://get.slack.help/hc/en-us/articles/115000769927-Message-threads" target="_blank">Slack recently added</a>), but without a way to edit posts (only delete), Slack serves this purpose better. The other thing happening in here is the <strong>Calendar</strong>. It gives a nice overview of the tasks that are being done so if you have to line up a particular project task with a project timeline, this is where you’re going to end up.&nbsp;</p><h2>Projects</h2><p>Also under the Team umbrella, there’s the ubiquitous <strong>Project</strong>. Our Projects range from an internal Social Media <a href="https://asana.com/guide/help/views/boards" target="_blank">board</a>, to prospective client projects and everything in between. Basically it helps keep all the projects organized we need to keep up with our clients’ growing business demands. The view for all of our Projects defaults to a list of Incomplete Tasks, recently switched over from a view that shows each of our tasks segmented by team member. I’ll get into why we did this and why it's so important, a little later. &nbsp;</p><h2>Tasks</h2><p>Tasks is where most of us work, most often. Speaking for most everyone, this is where we spend the most time. Moving from Projects to Tasks allows you to move out of the sidebar and into one of Asana’s major selling points and a large reason <a href="http://activatorstudios.com/project-management/why-we-dropped-trello-for-asana/" target="_blank">we switched from Trello</a>. In the top navigation, lives <strong>My Tasks</strong>. Or your Tasks. Or whatever. All you need to know is that it’s the place where all your stuff is. It’s a hub for everything you’re responsible for.&nbsp;This view, like our other Projects, defaults to Incomplete Tasks, but it didn’t used to. But before I go into how we used to use it, here's why the default view is so important:&nbsp;<strong>it's the first screen you see when you click on a Project, or a team member, or anything else.</strong>&nbsp;So in the name of productivity, you want that view to be the least cumbersome as possible. You don't want to waste time wading through junk to find what you need. That said, here’s the (much less efficient) way we used to do it:&nbsp;we'd sort tasks per project which is great and super organized in theory, but we found that it didn’t give us a sense of when tasks were due. In other words, form &gt; function. We often need to bounce from one project to the next to make sure all our clients are being taken care of, so being able to see a list segmented not by project or client, but by due date was critical. But sometimes, due dates aren’t set in stone. So for a while we were lacking something for us to sort tasks in a more flexible way. That is, until we discovered the ability to “mark” tasks instead of setting a due date.&nbsp;We've gotten into the habit of marking them as <em>Today</em>,<em>&nbsp;Upcoming</em>, or <em>Later</em>. They’re specific enough to help each of us get an overview of what everyone else is working on for the day or the week, but loose enough that we’re not chained to a due date. Tasks marked<em>&nbsp;Today</em>&nbsp;are surprise surprise, what we plan to work on or finish today. The most pressing tasks on your plate.&nbsp;<em>Upcoming,&nbsp;</em>are for tasks that need to be done in the very near future, like within a week for example. These are of medium urgency.&nbsp;<em>Later,&nbsp;</em>are tasks that don’t need to be addressed for another week or so, or something that requires more information from the client. These aren’t urgent tasks, but tasks that should be sitting in the back of your mind to get done when the other, more urgent tasks are done. So what we do now is make sure every one of our tasks are marked as <em>Today</em>,&nbsp;<em>Upcoming</em>, or <em>Later</em>&nbsp;then in the Incomplete Task view, we can work based on what’s due next. Tasks not marked will show up under New Tasks. And the best part, Asana will update the Incomplete View automatically as tasks are marked. Asana will only let you change the default Project view at the Team level (meaning, it can only default to a view for everyone at once), which at first was frustrating, because we all have our ways we like to work throughout the day. But, over time, we found it forces us all to stay on the same page and another inadvertent benefit, has helped us steer our daily stand-ups. &nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Tags</strong>&nbsp;You'll find <strong>Tags</strong>&nbsp;in pretty much any project management tool out there, and the function is basically the same across the board,&nbsp;too. It's a useful feature especially in Asana to group similar tasks together. Right now, we’re using Tags for the sole purpose determine which Tasks are “Roadblocked”, either by the client or another team member, by using a tag that’s literally, “roadblock”. That way, at a glance, we can see which tasks need to be prioritized over others. We started out using Tags as a way to group Tasks based on service area (<a href="http://activatorstudios.com/expertise/content/">Content</a>,&nbsp;<a href="http://activatorstudios.com/expertise/design/">Design</a>,&nbsp;<a href="http://activatorstudios.com/expertise/engineering/">Engineering</a>, or <a href="http://activatorstudios.com/expertise/digital-marketing/">Marketing</a>). And while useful in certain situations it turns out, being able to see all the tasks belonging to a particular service area isn’t really helpful for us. So the jury is still out on this particular feature and how it’s going to help us going forward. Asana’s web app packs a ton of function and does so quite nicely. And as our clients’ needs change and we add more people to our team it’s the project management app we found best equipped to handle that growth. Our workflow is still being optimized, but we’ve definitely hit a stride in our individual and collective workflow with Asana.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/png" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/591cf0b6f7e0ab48fd7625e7/1545517126744/1500w/6f2413.png" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1200" height="630"><media:title type="plain">How We Use Asana</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Why We Dropped Trello for Asana</title><category>project-management</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 00:53:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/5/17/why-we-dropped-trello-for-asana</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:591cecadbf629a201c75ca15</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>That’s right. After a four-month stint using Trello, we decided to make a change. <strong>We'll explain why</strong>. We’re a remote agency that <a href="http://activatorstudios.com/work/" target="_blank">makes super cool stuff</a> for clients across the country. We juggle projects with the dexterity of an aspiring circus performer and found ourselves in need of project management (PM) software that blended with our rapid workflow.</p><p>So we thought Trello might do the trick.</p><p>It was made for a more agile workflow, allowed us to keep projects and tasks updated and clearly marked their progress. It seemed like this really useful, trendy thing that larger product companies were using and knew it'd be perfect for us too. There were however, after a few months, some shortcomings we just couldn’t continue to overlook:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>To complete a task, we needed to drag each task to the correct list (you can finally mark a task complete!)</p></li><li><p>Time tracking options weren’t attractive or intuitive</p></li><li><p>The lack of visibility would make things difficult for us as our team scaled</p></li><li><p>The interface itself isn't as well-designed as some of the other options out there (let’s face it, we like nice things)</p></li></ul><p>So what exactly were we looking for? Well, we started by writing out a short list of 100% non-negotiables. Features we all agreed needed to be much better than Trello for us to even continue the conversation. The two primary features we listed were an easy way to keep tabs of:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Monthly tasks for existing clients</p></li><li><p>Tasks for new client projects</p></li></ul><p>Aside from that, there were a few others that weren’t <em>quite</em>&nbsp;as important, but they were up for very little debate, knowing they would make our jobs as PM’s, Designers, Engineers and Content strategists much easier.</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p>Better project organization for the PM</p></li><li><p>Better individual task organization</p></li><li><p>Ability to find what we needed, when we needed it without too much effort</p></li><li><p>Get a quick overview of a project/person’s tasks for the day/week]</p></li><li><p>Seamless time tracking integration options</p></li></ul><p>We did some testing with platforms that promised they’d fill that emptiness we felt, but failed to deliver for one reason or another. A few of us had experience with Basecamp in the past, for example, but despite the v3 overhaul its’ previous version left too bad of a taste in our mouths to continue.</p><p>Then in walks Asana.</p><p>This shiny, well-designed web app with <a href="https://asana.com/apps" target="_blank">no shortage of integrations</a>&nbsp;with enough options to scale with us as our company grew. So what did that transition look like? Well, we had 15 or so ongoing projects of varying sizes, all with their own tasks, comments and files attached to them. So naturally, we moved everything over manually.</p><p>Let me explain.</p><p>By this point, Trello was getting away from us. Trello commanded too much of our attention. It didn’t take long for us to realize it was time to start severing ties. We knew which projects we needed to migrate over and which ones to sunset. We blocked off a few days, each of us took a bucket of projects to move over and got to work. We removed tasks that were no longer relevant, already done or had become irrelevant as a project evolved. Now, several months in, and we're all generally happier. We'll continue to use the features Asana has to offer and tweak if we need to, but so far, so good. In hindsight, Trello, it seemed, was great at handling individual tasks and had to be further finessed to include multiple projects. While Asana on the other hand, is much better equipped to handle full-fledged projects and the nuances that came along with them. And with <a href="https://blog.asana.com/2016/11/introducing-boards/" target="_blank">Asana’s new Boards feature</a>, Trello is slowly becoming a distant memory. What PM tool do you use?&nbsp;We'll soon be sharing in more detail how Asana fits into our workflow.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/png" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/591cecadbf629a201c75ca15/1545517138620/1500w/Trello-vs-Asana.png.png" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1024" height="512"><media:title type="plain">Why We Dropped Trello for Asana</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>My Young Black Life</title><category>personal-essay</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/5/2/my-young-black-life</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:59088773725e250c61283c73</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Let me first say that this unapologetically black piece will make you a bit uncomfortable. My white friends will read this and think…hell, I don’t know what they’ll think. Nor do I care, really. It’s not something I talk about with them. I’m scared it’ll make them uncomfortable and alter our friendship in some profound way. But, and I’m just thinking out loud here, if we really are friends shouldn’t they, despite their own comfort or lack thereof, try to meet me in the middle and be understanding of my feelings?</p><p>Well, yeah, of course they should. Anyway.</p><p>My journey as a young black male in America, in the South, was marked with a few events that did well to foretell what life would be like as I move through this white world.</p><p>In kindergarten, my best friend, Jon O’Hara, a pale-faced kid with long blonde hair cut into a bowl, would take his hand and sweep the hair from his face with every lull in a conversation. A movement I apparently envied, because I remember mimicking his gestures completely unaware my short, usually nappy hair, was different and had not, nor will it ever, need to be swept from my face.</p><p>Four years later, I realized what it meant to be black. It was February, and the necessary Black History media was being displayed for us by our teacher, Ms. Williams, a black, middle-aged woman. The protests, both silent and violent, the brutality of the subsequent punishments, were all on exhibit for our malleable minds.</p><p>But it wasn’t until the video of MLK’s speech, when he so eloquently expressed his truths and his hopes for this country, did I realize he was talking about me. Putting two and two together (I was never one to slack in math class) the facade that blanketed my world fell with like a magician’s big reveal. My eyes left the screen, darted around, and for the very first time, saw the division of color. At the moment, the innocence we’re supposed to harness as children left my body. I saw the world for what I thought it was.</p><p>A year after that was the first time I got called a nigger. Nothing really prepares you for that. The weight of that word in the just the right context is enough to uproot the thoughts and feelings you’ve, until then, accepted as truth. I remember everything about that moment like it happened yesterday. I remember the who, what, when, where but not necessarily the ‘why’. I don’t think I was meant to understand the last one. You could chalk it up to kids being kids, but the malice with which it was said debunks that notion.</p><p>You start to wonder that if this guy, Chris Cheeks, has the gall to actually say the word, how many to their better judgement, are just thinking it? After that, the poignant ingredient of skepticism was then mixed in with the ever-present intelligence and curiosity I’d already possessed.</p><p>From there the prejudice concealed itself a little better. The being followed in stores, the dull “click” of locking doors as I passed, the ever-popular crossing of the street or clutching of the purse as I drew near. I became aware of it all. The narrow-minded that still considered me a threat, no thanks to the media, despite how well I dressed, can’t or won’t distinguish me from any of the other black guys roaming the street. (Yes, this still happens.)</p><p>But I grew up nicely. You know, in the burbs. Back when the burbs were more like utopias for white people and the cities remained un-gentrified and much less “cool”. My city, anyway.</p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gK8Qu9FUqF8" target="_blank">“We gentrified, we victimized, we fighting for survival…” — Vince Staples ain’t never lied.</a></p><p>My first black friend didn’t come till around middle school. I was raised in white spaces. Popular black culture wasn’t something I’d been accustomed to. My first lessons came late into elementary school. The guys on the traveling basketball teams I’d been a part of were my teachers. They presented the landscape of rap and hip-hop, its’ culture, many nuances and debated the differences between the two. I was enthralled. The dances, the attire, the swagger, all became part of my arsenal. I left those transformative years with the ability to adapt my mannerisms and behaviors to “fit the room”.</p><p>My middle and high school years were spent hanging with a rotating cast of characters, sharpening my skills as a chameleon along the way. From the privileged, well-adjusted team captain of the lacrosse team to a friend that wound up begging on the corner.</p><p>When it was time for college, I ended up choosing a local HBCU. It wasn’t my first choice. It was the only choice that was feasible at the time due to a series of unfortunate events. During this time, I lived at home, insulated by the false comfort of that largely-white suburb, not privy to the unique campus culture I would later revere. If I were honest with myself, at the time I thought of myself as better than the people I shared classrooms with. My comfortable home life and perceived intelligence made me “better than”. I needed to believe that to keep the insecurities at bay.</p><p>The internships in which I chose to participate were in white spaces with well-meaning white people. The black buoy in a sea of white is where I thought I wanted and needed to be. I see now that I could’ve taken a different route. Could have done so much more for the community I once resided. I was young and didn’t have all the information. I now try to make up for lost time, and recover lost opportunities. I look around in my Brooklyn neighborhood and quietly wonder what I missed out on by not immersing myself in the black college culture that was right under my nose for all those years. I wonder constantly if there’s more I could do.</p><p>As 30 looms, I seek blackness more than any other time in my life. It’s more essential I be around people that look like me. I don’t know why.</p><p>I have to constantly remind myself that every aspect of my life is just as valid and relevant as my white counterparts. That being said, I’m careful where I go, when I go, what aisles I traverse at the grocery store, who’s there, not to make sudden movements, what I wear, to always smile, to try and dull the sharpness of the black, bearded, tattooed body I find myself in every morning. I have an irrational fear of police.&nbsp;They react, move and make decisions off instinct. So do I, but I’m not so naive to think I’m given the same leeway as they, so I’m careful to tread on this earth lightly, though a little less so as I age.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/59088773725e250c61283c73/1545517058318/1500w/" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1066"><media:title type="plain">My Young Black Life</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>What I Need From a Design Meetup</title><category>design</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 23:12:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/5/2/what-i-need-from-a-design-meetup</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:59090422e3df284d84c34efb</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Design meetups here in Raleigh, NC are plentiful, and many of them have great content and great people leading them. I’ve been to some of those, and I’ve also been to some that have been less than perfect. They have been a place of solace, a place to listen and chat about design, and somewhere I can meet like-minded people. So whenever a new design meetup or other design-related group crops up, there are some criteria I am looking for before deciding to attend.</p><h2>Inclusive content</h2><p>Inclusive content involves the usage of words and imagery that are representative of all groups of people.&nbsp;<a href="http://www.uua.org/lgbtq/welcoming/ways/200008.shtml" target="_blank">Inclusive language is a broad topic</a>, but it’s also the first hook for me when searching for a new design meetup to join. One meetup that’s doing it right is The Iron Yard in Durham.</p><p>The main reason I would be inclined to go to this design meetup is the language in the description. Particularly, this sentence:&nbsp;<em>“Our doors are open to everyone who wants to learn about technology, from kids to people who want to change careers.”</em></p><p>It just screams, “Hey, we’re here to help no matter who you are!”</p><p>The content of a design meetup is important, and it is a clear reflection of what kind of atmosphere to expect. If I don’t feel comfortable, then I’m not interested.</p><h2>Stimulating conversation</h2><p>Once I find a design meetup to participate in, the next standard I look for is relevant and thought-provoking conversations. For instance, I recall a design meetup with the <a href="http://triuxpa.org/" target="_blank">Triangle chapter of the UXPA</a>. The presenter talked about <a href="https://vimeo.com/110024830" target="_blank">designing on the z-axis</a>. Part of the way through, I realized I had been thinking about design in two dimensions and not taking into account how much my designs could benefit from that third dimension. It blew my mind.</p><p>The next day in the office, the first thing I did was call an impromptu design meeting and made every single one of our designers watch the video. A year later, it still comes up in conversations and it is something we take into account with all our designs.</p><h2>A sharp facilitator</h2><p>I have been in too many design meetups where the facilitator just isn’t comfortable speaking in front of a group of people or moderating a crowd.&nbsp;One meetup I used to attend regularly, Function Pink, brought in different speakers for each one to talk about something they cared about. That’s nothing revolutionary. What was revolutionary, though, is how the <a href="http://lesjames.com/" target="_blank">group’s facilitator Les James</a>&nbsp;steered the conversations after the presentation.&nbsp;</p><p>If he thought a question or comment was a little off topic, he would address it quickly and move on without wasting any extra time on it. And if he felt there could be more layers to a question or comment, he would push that person or the group to peel back those layers to get to a deeper level conversation. Preparation is key.</p><h2>Consistency</h2><p>After I have attended a few design meetups, the next factor — and possibly the most critical one — is how consistently the group meets. Consistency is important to grow the number of attendees, which has a positive effect for people who join that group in the future. Around here, it happens way too often that I see an interesting design meetup that meets once every three months — if I’m lucky.</p><h2>Community</h2><p>There’s a level of comfort that comes with being a part of a community, and being comfortable in a design group makes it easier to ask questions, leads to better collaboration and, causes relationships to form faster. Creating and caring for that community will pay off if done right.</p><p>In a perfect world, every design meetup I attend would have all these characteristics. I have lost interest in the design groups that I have been a part of in the past, but I will &nbsp;continue searching for the next design group that is inclusive and consistent with great conversations.</p><p>Check out my next post where I will focus on design conferences, including some of my issues with their exclusionary aspects and ways they can improve for future events.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/59090422e3df284d84c34efb/1545517105745/1500w/" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">What I Need From a Design Meetup</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Bridging the Client Communication Gap</title><category>project-management</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 23:10:00 +0000</pubDate><link>http://revisionpath.com/bridging-the-client-communication-gap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:5909039be58c62b91c82ca0b</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Chances are you’ve worked on a client project that didn’t go as smoothly as you would have liked. This could be due to a number of things, but more often than not communication is at the core. Designers need to have a little empathy to understand what it’s like to be a client who wants the world but also be knowledgeable enough to rein in expectations. So here are some things you should tell your clients to fill potential communication gaps in your projects.</p><h2>“You need to be a part of this process.”</h2><p>You’ll end up with a more usable, higher quality product if your client is involved throughout the project. While they may not be thinking about the end result from a user’s perspective, they are thinking from an equally important point of view — a stakeholder.</p><p>Stakeholders are a significant part of the project process and can shed light on how any design decisions will affect their bottom line. On the other side of that, there could be features users are asking for that technically, are feasible, which a stakeholder could deem logistically impossible.</p><p>This is all valuable knowledge you can use to improve your design and your process. Plus, you’re empowering the client to have tangible input in that design process which makes for a happier client — and less work for you!</p><h2>“There may be hiccups along the way.”</h2><p>There could be times during the project where communication will breakdown, such as a late deliverable or a disagreement on design choices. These issues are almost always small and easily fixable, but the key to avoiding these is keeping in contact with your client and letting them know early on if potential issues are on the horizon.</p><h2>“We will not be able to accomplish everything you want.”</h2><p>There are a couple reasons you may wind up having this conversation with your client during a project; a tight deadline or something they want would be a clear detraction from the user’s experience.</p><p>Every project you encounter will have a deadline. And if the communication with your client isn’t flawless from the beginning, there will be items that are a part of the project scope that just won’t get done. You must prioritize. If the client is asking for something that you think shouldn’t be as high up on the priority list, speak up. They need to know that you have a plan in mind for what the project is going to be.</p><p>Also in any project, the experience of your users takes precedence. The client has their idea of how they want their site to look and function but if any aspect of that doesn’t benefit the user, or worse, take away from or limit their experience in any way, then it’s your job to make sure the client is aware of that. Taking away from the user’s experience could be the addition of an obtrusive pop-up window or as simple as a font suggestion that you know isn’t right for their typical user.</p><h2>“Here’s why I’m doing this.”</h2><p>There needs to be some level of educating your client with every project. The client hired you for your knowledge and expertise, so you need to remind them that you are the expert in this situation. Explain design or UX principles to support your project choices. Or, better yet <em>show</em>&nbsp;them the steps you took to get to your decision. Walking them through your thought process not only gives them insight to how you work, but it ensure you and your client remain on the same page throughout the project.</p><p>Client work is hardly a painless process, and I doubt it ever will be. But by taking these steps to communicate effectively with my client, this will improve experiences of all parties and increase the likelihood for future collaboration.</p><p><a href="https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/5/2/bridging-the-client-communication-gap">Permalink</a><p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/5909039be58c62b91c82ca0b/1545517147499/1500w/" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Bridging the Client Communication Gap</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Why I Work for Free</title><category>design</category><dc:creator>James Jackson</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 23:08:00 +0000</pubDate><link>http://revisionpath.com/why-i-work-for-free/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83:59080045c534a53150517aaf:59090342db29d6a015344092</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>We’ve all done our share of free labor in the past; on occasion, I still do. Even at this point in my career, I’m not above working for free under the right circumstances. Here are four questions I ask myself before taking on my next unpaid project.</p><h2>Do I care about this company’s mission?</h2><p>If I don’t feel an emotional connection to the purpose or the mission of the company, then I’m probably not interested in doing work for them. For me, there has to be a level of altruism in the product or service they’re providing that I want to be associated with. This is first on the list for a reason — it’s the main deciding factor.</p><h2>Will I still be interested three months from now?</h2><p>This is important for me because I tend to have “shiny object syndrome”, and I sometimes bounce from one new project to the other. If I think a project is capable of holding my attention for longer than a couple months, the chances of me taking it on increases significantly.</p><h2>Would my portfolio benefit from the work?</h2><p>If there’s an aspect of a project that allows me to add something new and different to my portfolio, that increases the a chance I will take on the project. I think we can all agree that having quality pieces in your portfolio is a good thing! Projects that I’ve pursued in the past like these have included style guides, logos and websites that allowed me to stretch my skills.</p><h2>Is the client a good fit for me?</h2><p>I struggle with this one. I’ve been burned in the past by not answering this question honestly. It’s no fun working with people that don’t share my views or who aren’t willing to at least try to see things from my perspective. It’s an absolute deal-breaker. If the relationship is new, then I proceed with caution and always give myself an out of some kind, normally through the language I use in contracts. If it happens to be a more familiar relationship, I have a little more leeway but I still have to make sure I’m not being taken advantage of for the sake of the project.</p><p>Even with these questions, one great thing about working for free is the opportunity it provides me to pick up or put down a project at a moment’s notice. Beggars can’t be choosers, and if my series of questions served me well and I ended up choosing the right client, then they won’t give me too much grief should a paid project come along. It’s a bit of a balancing act when these situations come up. I love the autonomy that comes with free work, but I also know my time and skill hold a certain value.</p><p>So let me be clear: As creative people, we all need to know our value. I recognize when to charge what I know I’m worth, but every now and then a project comes along that passes my criteria that I really feel good about and want to be a part of building. In those cases, I work for free.</p><p><a href="https://www.jamesdarin.work/writing/2017/5/2/why-i-work-for-free">Permalink</a><p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5907f77d5016e17b11bb1d83/59080045c534a53150517aaf/59090342db29d6a015344092/1545517157160/1500w/" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="994"><media:title type="plain">Why I Work for Free</media:title></media:content></item></channel></rss>